Okay, then I got to ask you about the
Fibonacci line. [music]
>> Fibonacci sequence.
>> Was it intentional that five, two, and
three are Fibonacci numbers, but in the
wrong order?
>> What's her name? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I did
it back
cuz you if you listen to my music, I
flip stuff all the time. I always say it
one way and I'll say it back.
>> Carl Lewis. Lewis and Clark. Yeah.
>> You feel me? So with the Fibonacci, I
was like, "Somebody's going to catch
this. Somebody knows it's going to go.
[laughter] It's the golden rule."
Something like that. I always miss the
>> golden mean. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah,
>> everyone out there. It's
>> every single thing is intentional.
[laughter]
I know
>> that's what I'm saying.
>> I'm such a jittery person as you
probably think, but the fact that you
caught little stuff like that,
>> it just means like I'm I'm doing it
right.
>> This episode of Dissect is presented by
Amazon Prime. The holidays hit fast. One
moment you're planning, the next
everything's out of sync. Luckily, Prime
helps you catch the rhythm with fast,
free delivery that gets it there just in
time. [music] Prime's fast shipping is
always there for you during the
holidays, especially when it's last
minute and it just can't wait. hosting
essentials or the gift that hits the
right note. It's on Prime. Head to
amazon.com/prime
to shop now.
Welcome everyone to a special episode of
Dissect. I'm your host Cole Kushna.
Today we're very honored to have J in
the building to dissect his [music]
brand new Grammy nominated album, God
Does Like Ugly. Jid, thanks for uh being
on Dissect.
>> Thanks for having me, bro.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Congratulations on the
Grammy nod. How did it feel?
>> It was cool. Um,
>> just that is like actually mine, you
know what I'm saying? My nomination
opposed to like other projects I've been
involved in.
>> So, it's a blessed feeling, you know
what I'm saying? Having like a group of
your peers
>> say this is what you guys need to listen
to or whatever the case may be. [music]
[music]
>> Okay, so I want to get into as much as
the album as we can. I always like to
start with the album title. I know
there's a story about your grandma, the
origin of the title, but so maybe for
those that haven't heard that yet, you
can relay that story. But I'm also
interested about how this kind of
off-the cuff thing that she said to you
developed into what feels like the
thematic framework of the entire album.
>> Yeah. So, um, initially my grandmother,
don't know what I don't know exactly
what the occurrence was going on in the
world, but I just remember her saying if
God letting that happen, he God must
like ugly or something like that,
something in that regard. And it just
stuck with me. You know what I'm saying?
Cuz I'm used to hearing the term God
doesn't. You know what I'm saying? So,
>> just her being creative enough to just
flip that on its head and it kind of
sent me for a loop. This is around 2019
before she passed. And it stuck with me
all those years just working on the
music and trying to find something
around that um that just felt uh
authentic to the title cuz the title
wasn't going to change,
>> right?
>> All the music even in the creation of
it, bro. It's not the album that I uh it
didn't come together all the way I
thought it did. I had a lot of different
samples and stuff that didn't get
cleared and just
But it worked out. It turned out to be
like a project that I love.
>> I I that's the only reason I put it out
is because I like it. I wasn't bashing
it on offions of anybody
>> for the most part besides like my team
and stuff like that. But I'm sorry.
>> You know, a show that everybody like you
trying to get in LA show. [laughter]
>> Um
that's actually absole too.
>> Hilarious enough. just [snorts]
more more selfishly like saying, "Okay,
this is what I think the the wave is,
and this is how I feel about the music."
And
>> I'm not even sure like
>> people would uh be it's a ugly project.
It was meant to be like
>> right
>> a little uncomfortable in some spaces.
>> Yeah, there's a lot I mean just as
compared to your last work uh and
forever story, there's a lot. It feels
more gritty. Feels like more you're I
mean in the opening line we'll talk
about your the depths of hell is the
first line on the you know there's this
really kind of grit to it. I'm wondering
[snorts]
>> the idea of what what is ugly seems like
to be one of the central questions of
the album. How one defines ugly, what
the world considers ugly.
>> Um so I guess like as we're talking
about the album title, I mean what does
ugly mean to you?
Um,
>> in in terms of this project, yeah,
>> in terms of this project, it's really
just your own perception. It's not like
being a u a part of the crowd. You know
what I'm saying? That's kind of what it
is. It's kind of individuality
>> and however you see it. And like
>> it could be like a one man trash,
another man's treasure type situation.
>> But in my mind, it just leans right into
just like being whatever you are, even
if it stands outside of the norms of
whatever
you may see that as. So,
>> right,
>> that's kind of where like I stood with
the project.
>> Yeah, it's interesting. We'll talk about
um Pastor Troy's uh vice versa, but it
feels like this idea of how outsiders
what what you know outsiders call ugly
um and almost taking pride in an
ugliness because maybe we can get into
the first track. You literally say you
ugly is the title of the first track.
Um, and then we hear Westside Guns voice
is the first thing we hear on that. And
he right away like redefineses ugly.
He's calling his girl ugly. He's calling
his shoes ugly in like a positive way.
>> Flyway,
>> right?
>> U00
[__]
>> Did Westside have a verse or did you
always just imagine him as this kind of
like orator narrator? Um, we started off
with
him
uh finding some production. Um, I wanted
him to curate the song specifically and
he did that amazingly. You know what I'm
saying? Came through with the the
production and the words he was saying.
So, I really didn't need a verse, but I
wouldn't wasn't opposed to it because I
love when he raps.
Um, [snorts]
but for the most part it was really in
setting the stage for it and we went
through a bunch of different channels
with production because like samples and
all of that stuff and we got to a place
where there's no samples on that record
specifically and then
just making it a kind of like a a jump
scare in the middle of the record when
you have like oh west side I'm rapping
ceiling challenge show my pitch and then
you have this beautiful melodic
breakdown
the words kind uh describing the
feelings that you just heard a little
bit,
>> but it's preparing you for a whole
another journey on the the back half of
it,
>> right?
>> But still going with the same intentions
and lines just explaining my narrative
and explaining how I felt. Sometimes
people try to like I don't know. I don't
know what people try to do, but I wasn't
trying to like go too far over your head
with the writing
>> or
>> just kind of trying to be more direct.
just a couple of things, uh, metaphors
and all that stuff, it's gonna be there.
But
>> it was more a direct approach to it. So,
if you listen to that, if you listen to
the project with that thought in mind,
it's just like directly telling you what
it is. It kind of gives you more of an
easiness when you're listening to it
opposed to like
Forever Story, I'm barring you up,
giving you all type of simileies,
metaphors, different stories, and it's
all polished.
>> That was the thing about Forever Story.
I wanted to make it feel polished and
beautiful, bright. You know what I'm
saying? You get in this story, you get
clouds and [__] stars and all the
rainbows and [__]
>> Right. Right.
>> But on this one, I just wanted to feel
like a constant dark cloud
>> until damn near the end.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I like how that first verse goes
into the gospel bridge and you're kind
of getting
>> it feels like you're setting up the
world of the album, like where things
might be headed. You're kind of it's
like the the sun peeking through the the
clouds for a moment and then
>> it's literally the worst what you just
said. It's literally tomorrow will bring
sunny sunny skies.
>> I said
talking about crying.
>> Dear Lord about community leaders
there's tears in my eyes. I know
>> there's tears in my eyes. I know
tomorrow will bring sunny skies and I
will look back and smile cuz it's just a
moment in time
for a [__] challenge to show above my
peers.
>> [music]
>> tears in my eyes
[music]
tomorrow.
>> So that that kind of theme of dark and
light. I feel like it runs throughout
the entire project and you kind of I
love the opening line of the project
where you say lie from the depths of
hell. So you get this dark imagery but
right away with angel wings that have
yet to flail.
>> Yeah. which I feel like kind of spells
out a lot of what the project is talking
about kind of people coming from these
darker places. The potential they're
born pure, born with angel wings just
not giving the opportunities or their
circumstances not allowing them to to
fully blossom into their potential.
>> Um, and I love that second line and fans
argue about record sales like they
recorded exact themselves just like
>> that's just hilarious, right?
Well, the rhyme schemes are [__]
great, by the way. Thank you. [music]
>> Wings have yet to fans argue about
records like record exaches [music]
you well.
>> Was the idea like we're focused on the
wrong thing?
>> Yeah, 100%. That's all it was.
>> Um,
art. It's like
uh we sell our art, but at the same time
it's like priceless. You know what I'm
saying? The places that it come from, if
it's natural and it's organic and
beautiful, like
if if the art makes you feel something,
I don't think
the consumption or the people that's if
it's a majority thing, like I don't
think that's the that's hurt mentality.
You know what I'm saying? And I feel
like we've been like kind of plagued by
that in today's age and stuff like that.
So I just wanted to speak to that, but
not like dis fans like you know what I'm
saying? Not this, but also it's like we
kind of missing the ball a little bit on
what this music could be or
>> right
>> the the medicine it provides. You know
what I'm saying? To some people. And
>> it's medicine to me. So
>> I don't think just the price on it. The
numbers and stuff is cool. It was nice
when you got the accolades. I would love
I want the biggest accolades in the
world.
>> You know what I'm saying? Not saying I
don't. I care about I I'm not a numbers
guy, but of course if you about to have
a number one on Billboard or you doing
you're going to lean into it. And
there's nothing wrong with that.
>> But it can't be the the the bottom line.
>> Yeah.
>> You know what I'm saying? It can't be
the talking point of if Mick Jenkins had
one of the best projects of the year, I
think. You know what I'm saying?
I I I think stuff like that is
outside of the that kind of devalues
what we do a little bit.
>> Yeah.
>> Cuz like I said, like one of my favorite
projects this year. I'm not sure how
many people heard it, but the MC Jenkins
album is something I just been living
with and just
>> loving it because he's just one of those
type of artists that pull that out of
you and it wasn't even like the happiest
feelings. It was kind of like
>> made you feel a little bit aggressive,
but to that point. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, um, so in the opening
verse as well, you introduce your older
brother, uh, who feels like a recurring
character in the album.
>> Yeah.
>> I guess for those not familiar with the
story,
>> maybe convey that if you're comfortable
with that. And also like why because he
comes up
>> on this song, comes up on Glory. Um, so
I guess how how like why did you want to
use your brother's story? Is there any
kind of kind of thematic symbolism that
you thought his story could represent?
I ain't even get no bail [music] on his
third strike. And if you serve life,
them crackers probably like that serve
you right. [__] too real. Just gave me
chill. The devil's
>> through my life. This is my So I'm I'm
I'm the youngest of seven, but I'm
detached by a bunch of years. I feel
like my brother's almost um you're
almost 50, but he been in jail like my
whole life.
>> Mhm.
>> You know what [clears throat] I'm
saying? In and out. And before this
project was another time he went back to
jail. So, I'm dealing with that and
writing an album. He's heavy on my mind.
Um,
and that was just kind of like the anger
and the exhaustion, the stress like my
family's been dealing with cuz once you
got like a family member in jail, it's
kind of like all of y'all in there.
>> Yeah.
>> Especially like my mother. So, and
that's her. I have a blended family. So,
that's her son with her ex-husband. And
I just see the stress and everything she
go through dealing with that. And it
makes me expressive of it. Even if I'm
not telling you like the exact
throughout my timeline, you you you
probably understand what my brother did
through my my albums, my discoraphy. I
talk about them every single album, but
this one specifically just cuz he went
back into jail
>> and
he he didn't get a bail for he's been
sitting waiting for 3 four years on bail
since I since I dropped the last
project. Cuz if you see
>> the uh Smack On video, he was in there.
>> You know what I'm saying? And then this
3 years later and he's still dealing
with what he dealing with. Um so it
would just take me to a place um of just
questions
um think about his mind state my
mother's mind state my parents um a lot
of things come a rush of emotions
waterfall of emotions but
>> I just try to give him love and just
like
talk through his like through his life
through my eyes the way I see it.
It's kind of like a It's like a
action-packed like movie. You know what
I'm saying? The stories that I hear
about him, the conversation we've had,
him being one of the first people I've
ever seen rap.
>> Um, it just adds a lot to it. So, God
does like ugly is just his story as
well. That's why I bring him up in the
first two songs and I refer to him
throughout the album all the time. The
glory is the whole song of glory is
about him,
>> okay?
>> From top to bottom. The person that I'm
talking about got baptized and all of
that. I'm talking about him and then I
just bring it back to the end when I say
like and I really let you know it's him.
My brother back inside a cell.
>> Mhm.
>> But yeah.
>> Yeah. I think I mean it's it's powerful
and as a listener cuz it's like um
you know with family members it's like
you're able to see more than their
mistakes. You know like sometimes when
you're looking just from a distance at
someone and you just see mistakes they
made but you know with family it's like
you you see them far beyond those
mistakes. Okay. Okay. So, we already
talked about the gospel bridge.
And then verse two, you issue somewhat
of a lyrical challenge. So, I got to
take you up on that. You you say uh you
ask about catching a bar. So, I got to I
got to ask you if I got it right. So,
the bar is you say J and Friends playing
Mario Kart, looking at my big brother
back in that mid um and moving around
the city like Louiswis and Clark. Hop
out the car. Turn to Carl Lewis. [music]
Kid and friends playing Mario car
looking at my big brother bagging at me.
Moving around the city like Louis
the car [music] turn if you bar you
understand why I do this when I was
little. [music]
>> If you caught that bar you understand
why I do this. So great word play with
the Louiswis and Clark.
>> Carl [clears throat] Lewis being this
Olympic athlete.
>> Yeah.
>> Runs track.
>> That's my dad name though.
>> Okay. That's Yeah,
>> there it is. [laughter]
>> Father's name Carl Lewis. Root. And then
you do you have an older brother named
Carl too? Yeah.
>> Okay. So the bar is essentially like I
do this for family, right?
>> Oh yeah, I was a friend. I'm glad you
caught that.
>> That's sick. Okay. And then you say
>> you don't know me if you know me since
Little Root, which was your childhood
nickname, right?
>> That's my last name.
>> Okay. Right.
>> So they always used to call me Little
Root.
>> Okay.
>> For sure. For sure.
>> All right. Lyrical challenge. Like I got
it right. [laughter]
>> I love it. I love that. I love that.
>> Okay. Um Okay, then I got to ask you
about the Fibonacci line. [music]
Stop me. I'm top five
top three and I don't know the Fibonacci
sequence. Put the numbers together.
>> You say I'm top five. Pop the clock two
times. Might be top three. And I don't
know the Fibonacci sequence. Put the
numbers together and something's got to
make sense. So was it intentional that
five, two, and three are Fibonacci
numbers but in the wrong way?
>> What's the name? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I did
it back. I did. You
>> if you listen to my music, I flip stuff
all the time. I always say it one way
and I'll say it back. Carl Lewis,
Louiswis and Clark. Yeah. Yeah.
>> You feel me? So with the Fibonacci, I
was like, "Somebody's going to catch
this. Somebody knows it's going to go.
[laughter] It's the golden rule or
something like that. I always [snorts]
mean." Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> That was sick. Okay, cool. Um, it's
intentional everyone out there. It's
>> every single thing is [laughter]
intentional. I know
>> that's what I'm saying.
>> I'm such a jittery person as you
probably think, but the fact that you
caught little stuff like that, it just
means like I'm I'm doing it right.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. There's there's some
of us that are really paying attention.
I love that kind of [__] It's my
favorite stuff.
>> Thank.
>> Okay. Okay. So then let's get into
glory. Um, one of my favorite songs on
the on the entire project.
>> Giving glory to God. I'm alert and
alive.
[music]
>> Sample is great. I know there's a pretty
interesting compelling story around the
production. I don't know if you want to
share that.
>> Uh, yeah. just essentially when I got
the production, we started going through
the clearing process after I had the
song done and it was a very obscure
sample from a choir from Memphis,
Tennessee. And they denied it initially.
I had cussing words and stuff and I
understand why they why they denied the
sample at first, but just being the type
of person I am growing up the way I am I
did, I wanted to go a little bit
further. You know what I'm saying? to
try and get clear and show the people
that like the type of man I am. So
I asked, "Can we speak?" I got my mother
on the phone cuz she's just like the
most beautiful southern lady. Like she
could um she just got she swag like she
know how to speak and she knows how to
carry herself and it's a beautiful
southern lady, church god-fearing lady
and that's what she instilled in me. So
I just wanted the person on the other
end of it to understand that sentiment
and the person who cleared it was very
close with the sample because her father
arranged the original choir
>> um however they sang that they arranged
that and she's very close to it. So got
on the phone, kind of gave her the idea
the type of people we are, spoke about
my faith, spoke to my mother, said,
"I'll make the changes, whatever it
needs to be." And we did it and they
cleared it. But before they cleared it,
they said, "We want to speak to you guys
one more time." I'm like, "Cool." And
when we spoke, she says they cleared it
and they did some research on me,
listened to my music, listened to
Forever Stories at the time. So if you
listen to the album and you get to know
me, it's like, "Oh, it's not stick." You
know what I'm saying? Listen to some
great riding, some real life experience
and
>> they enjoyed it specifically like swang
on and stuff like that, which is a negro
spiritual like it's some
>> something that's really close to me. So
her specifically liking these records.
>> [snorts]
>> um said she just wanted to pray over me
and my team and the family and stuff
>> cuz
>> using that sample specifically verbatim,
she said I'm going into a spiritual
battle, spiritual warfare in an industry
that doesn't like
>> lean towards that. You know what I'm
saying? It's more
>> dark if you would say in the industry.
So
>> when she said it, it kind of like threw
me for a loop. I'm like, whoa. Like you
understand like it's something special
about it. And she spoke
all this gr all this stuff that's
happening right now. She spoke it. She
said, "This project is going to be huge.
It's going to be one of the biggest
works." And I mean,
>> wow.
>> It's kind of crazy like that that
happened like that. And just really just
based in faith and we got together and
you know, more than two or three people
gathered. That's that's church. That's
what they say in the Bible or whatever.
That's like
>> powerful right there. So,
>> are they saying I can't make out what
they're saying. Are do you do you know
what they're saying in the sample?
>> No, sir.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
I was trying listening hard. I was
trying to Yeah. I couldn't make it out.
Uh,
>> but it's a fill in there. They're saying
glory, of course.
>> Okay. Right.
>> They're saying glory, but
>> it's just amazing. I don't even know.
>> You guys got some mileage out of it,
too. The way the production tweaks with
like the beat switch and it like goes
dark deeper and like it's so sick.
>> There's like three levels to it.
>> Yeah.
>> It starts off how it starts. The second
level you get a little bit darker and by
the time you're at the end of the song,
it's just giving you the pure intention,
the grit, the the fight through it. You
know what I'm saying?
[music] I'm against the odds trying to
get evil. See the evil in my eyes. Bes
is the Lord. [music] So I leave it up to
God. But if he don't move forward, I'mma
get me ming.
>> Interesting. The Zoom call. I was
wondering the context around that Zoom
call. It feels a little like rand, not
random, but like it's just like comes
out of nowhere, but then it like cues up
the beat switch. It's like a cool
contrast. But I was wondering like just
the purpose of that Zoom call as a skit.
Um, so if you listen to it, it sounds
like somebody uh that will represent
something from the business side of
music business. Um,
>> and that that was kind of funny to me
cuz it was it represents being kind of
dark like
>> we're about to get like you know what
I'm saying that money hungry.
>> Okay, that was okay.
>> Yeah, we can hear you now. Go ahead,
Victoria.
>> Hey guys. Hey J. Just getting back from
a meeting. the numbers are looking
[music]
>> the numbers and all of that stuff. I
just thought it was a funny thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Leading into
>> the last verse cuz
>> it's giving you a um
it's it's it's positive, but at the same
time, if you know like the industry and
how things go and stuff, it could be
like, "Oh, this could be a horrible
thing. All the money's coming, so it
means like
>> more more money, more problems." Type
[__] I I wanted I was thinking about it
in that realm.
>> Okay.
>> And like I said, I wasn't trying to be
too uh metaphorical and on this album.
I'm literally
>> if you listen to the words, you
understand what I'm getting. I'm not
trying to like beat you over the head
like the
>> I'm from the south. So, even the way I
speak, it it has to be direct. You know
what I'm saying? Because of the dialogue
and the way we use words and stuff like
that, you might understand it if I tried
to go like over over the top. So,
>> yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. The final verse has one of my
favorite lines on the project where you
say, "Open up the Bible and read a
chapter. I'm trying to free the
shackles. My brother back inside a cell,
so I just say a prayer in the Garden of
Eden." Say he couldn't help but eat the
apple. [music] So the pastor open the
Bible up and read a chapter. I'm trying
to free the shackles. My brother back
inside. So I just said a prayer in the
Garden of Eden say he couldn't help but
eat the apple. contextualizing your
brother's story but then tying it to the
story of humanity like was really
powerful. I don't know what the I don't
even break down the some of the
intention behind that one.
>> So you know Adam and Eve the temptation
>> right
>> essentially. So whatever his vices are
or whatever he said he couldn't help it
like whatever he did and I'm not going
to go into detail but
>> like he couldn't change that. You know
what I'm saying? It's just innately who
he is as a human. Like I don't know if
you take that as bad or good, but I just
wrote it to speak truth opposed to like
whatever, however anybody would feel,
but
I just know the type of man he is and he
like is no BS. You know what I'm saying?
So when when I spoke to him about
whatever occurred, you know what I'm
saying? His sentiment was like, bro, I
couldn't even and it was nothing like
too like crazy crazy like, bro, that had
to go. I had to run that, you know what
I'm saying? I had to do what I had to
do. And that's literally me bringing
that Bible and actual real life and kind
of bring them in so everybody could get
>> where I was going with it. And like I
said, it's just very simple, but I just
think it's a a swag, a way to bring them
like both together with the writing and
stuff
>> cuz I try to unlearn and relearn like
different writing techniques. You know
what I'm saying? I don't want to just be
the same type of rapper that you say a
bar and it's like, "Oh, this is like,"
you know what I'm saying? when they use
like as the I hate that. You know what
I'm saying?
>> And I try to like steer away from that.
>> That's why that
line or I don't even know what you would
consider that.
>> You know what I'm saying? The the
writing style of that,
>> right?
>> But that's why it came off like that. I
just think it's like good writing.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, we get the pastor
interspersed throughout Glory.
>> Yeah.
>> Um which I read was Kristo's dad, right?
Which Christo is your producer, longtime
producer. It's on all your albums.
>> That's kind of wild.
>> Yeah. Right. He's a He's a PK
>> which is cool cuz And I also think it's
cool cuz last time
>> my dad was like on the on the Forever
story. He was all over it. You know what
I'm saying? This time his father's all
over this project. So I think it's cool
to just
>> being able to add ancestors and legacy
part of the stuff that we're doing.
>> Yeah. Glory ends with the pastor kind of
saying like what God the work that God
does on on us and then we transition
into work.
[music]
>> So the sample on this is [__] really
cool and powerful in the background of
the song pretty subtly but once you hear
it it's like you you can't unhear at
least I can't. But there's a literal
work song.
>> Yeah. uh sampled. It's called Early in
the Morning recorded in 1948.
>> I was sung by four incarcerated black
men in Mississippi Penitentiary who are
forced to work on these essentially
extension of slavery forced prison labor
>> specifically.
>> You found that. That was sick. Okay.
>> For sure.
[music]
>> I can come and deliver the victory.
Well, tell me the story of that.
>> It just ties back into everything that I
be speaking about. Um
>> Okay. Did you have the concept uh work
and first and then found the sample or
did the sample come?
>> I had the concept. I did it all together
when I was writing the um the verse. I
had the production. Well, we did the
production in the studio and I I feel
like I went on YouTube or something and
just start looking up because I used the
prison songs specifically those guys.
I've used that before. It [snorts] could
have been on radar. I'm not 100% sure,
but something could have been on radar
from from them. But I used that because
I knew like, oh, this makes sense. This
is like closer to like my roots of what
I be talking about. It's like the
slavery [snorts] stuff, the prison,
>> you know what I'm saying? School, the
pipeline thing, that whole little world
right there. Um,
>> and yeah, I just thought the essence,
even if you didn't hear it all the way,
you could kind of feel it. You know what
I'm saying?
>> That's what I was trying to go with. No,
it's it's beautiful. And I also like how
it ties into the at least in my
perception ties into the theme of the
album because you have these men in this
really ugly situation creating beauty,
you know, creating these songs. You can
literally hear their axes on the
>> that create the rhythm of the song, you
know, so blending work um with this
beauty. Um just really cool, really cool
detail.
>> Okay, I got to ask you about the opening
line of this song. [music]
my drive if it were 1955 and I'm on 85
doing 95 and a 1952 Dodge so much.
>> So you say you couldn't even stop my
drive if it were 1955 and I'm on 85
doing 95 and a 952 Dodge.
>> Okay. So you said you're pretty direct
on this album, but this seems like it's
kind of coded with some stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So can I give you my breakdown?
You can tell me if it's right or or
wrong. Okay. Um, so couldn't stop my
drive. Obviously, your ambition,
you're referencing a literal car drive
in this metaphor.
>> Yeah.
>> I also read that this was inspired by
your football coach, so I was wondering
if there was like a football drive play
on
>> No, his thing was just let's go to work.
Like that was his old phrase.
>> Uh, okay. So 1955
was the year of the Montgomery boycott.
>> Um, tying in this idea of stop my drive.
They refused to to ride buses.
>> Y
>> the 85 is the interstate that connects
Atlanta to Montgomery. So connecting
your home
>> around the same time. So
>> Right. Yeah. Exactly. Um so yeah, so the
85 was built in 1958. So 3 years after
the boycott.
>> Yeah.
>> 52 Dodge 95 mph. Interesting. I don't
know if this might just be like crazy
reaching, but the fastest Dodge from
1952 only goes like 85 or 90.
>> Yeah. 859.
>> Okay. So, sounds like this was
intentional. So, essentially the play is
like even if the buses were down,
highway wasn't built yet cuz your
sighting year before it was built.
>> Yeah.
>> Car didn't go that fast. You still can't
drop stop my drive.
>> 100%.
>> Like a
>> You say you weren't being lyrical.
That's [laughter]
like so sick.
>> Yeah. No, it's I feel like it's
intention. It's just doing your history
and stuff like that. You know what I'm
saying? I I didn't know all of that. I
knew when boycotts and all of that stuff
was, but
>> I didn't know when 85 was built, so I
had to actually look that up. You didn't
be intentional about that. Um
>> Okay. So, how well break down like So,
where does the initial idea come from?
Is it just that opening line or like So,
how do you get into this get doing the
research? Like, how does that generate?
It started with the first line and I
decided I want to go with I wanted to go
with a number scheme.
>> And it's not really that crazy because
this why I say it's not that complex cuz
I use fives at the end of everything. I
just and I hate when rappers do that
sometimes when you rhyme a word with a
word you already said before. But I'm
like this is numbers. Suck my dick.
>> Um [snorts]
[laughter]
um
but yeah, the it literally started with
the initial line. You couldn't even stop
my drive if it was 1955. That's where
the the ideas start coming from cuz it's
like, okay, now we talking about this.
How can we
>> do more history lessons and try to like
give little inklings of what I'm talking
about. So, I looked up
>> when the first Dodge rhymes with five a
little bit. So, I'm like, hey, talking
about a car, when was the first car?
What was the fastest? What's the speed?
Looked up all of that stuff. And then I
went to the dates and
>> try to just make it all correlate to
like you not being able to stop my uh
intentions, my drive, my focus,
>> all of that stuff.
>> So sick. It's really cool. Thank you.
>> Okay, let's jump to Community.
>> Yeah,
>> it's one of the best rap songs I've ever
heard. This song is so good. Um, so
congratulations on making it. It's a
perfect song.
>> Thank you.
>> I'm confused by the intro. I'm wondering
if you could help me understand. So, you
go into like all these kind of natural
elements.
>> The rain couldn't understand it. The
pain [music] made them understand. [__]
The sun tried to understand. The gun
made me understand. the wind dry whisper
warning.
>> Really beautiful line. It all it kind of
culminates to this line. All the forces
like a portal to a vortex connected to
the stars just projecting where we part
at. And then you do this a a bunch on
this album where you take a reference to
childhood or like a reference to I don't
know something like sweet and then it
flips and in this case you flip it to
like this scene
>> where I think you're talking about guns
pull up where you park at aim a little
dark where you bark at.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, can you break down that
intro a little bit for me? This episode
is brought to you by Amazon Prime. The
holidays move fast, so stay in sync with
Prime's fast, free delivery. Admittedly,
I sometimes wait till the last minute to
buy my gifts, and I've been saved by
Prime more than a few times. That's
because Prime's fast shipping is always
there for you during the holidays,
especially when it's last minute and
can't wait. Need that final gift or
holiday essential in a flash? It's on
Prime. Head to amazon.com/prime
to shop now.
I started it off by just speaking about
like why things are so [__] up for
people in these uh living situations,
people of color in these living
situations. So it's like nobody
understands it. The rain couldn't
understand. The pain made you
understand. Son tried to understand the
gun made me understand. It's just that's
right there is hell of violence within
those words right there. And
just with how I grew up and stuff like
this, I know I I moved around probably
before I was 13, probably moved to 10
different cribs. You know what I'm
saying? Different communities,
horrible places, some middle class, some
apartments, all of that stuff. It kind
of just add into um
how I grew up, the visual
representation, the the black people
that I because I I will say this, I grew
up around all black people. I'm from
Atlanta, went to a black school, middle
school, high school, end up going to a
H.B.CU. So, my real first interaction
with a lot of other races and people
that's not all black like we're we're
now. It's kind of like when I came into
this industry and I'm like, "Oh, this is
the world." Driving the world kind of
opened up my eyes to let me know it's
not a lot of us out here. You know what
I'm saying? So, these small sections in
the corners of whatever state you say in
like it kind of has the same thing going
on. This it's hoods everywhere. It's a
it's a MLK like and it's going to be a
hood. Like those are two things you can
guarantee. So,
with the words and stuff, I was just
truly trying to explain
in a round not even a roundabout type of
way because you could understand what
I'm saying. Rain couldn't understand.
These are very simple terms and stuff
like that.
And I know I lost a question. I start
rambling a little bit.
>> That's all good. Yeah, just uh Well, I
just that it's just a beautiful way to
frame it, I think. Um
>> and then you go into the apartments. Um
that becomes kind of the main symbol of
the song.
>> Yeah.
>> Is that just got to go back into what
you're just saying?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. just really trying to um unpack
and um give like the instruction that I
was told told and
give a um it's a true perspective on how
I feel about these lowincome housing
neighborhoods and just the places people
were placed in without even have like
without an option. You know what I'm
saying? No choice.
>> I'll [music] put a bullet in the [__]
building and kick us out the building.
What about the children? When I check a
news channel, I get a similar feeling,
but still [music] we going to make it to
heaven, high water, and hell, but don't
take the house.
>> Got to ask you about the Bob the Builder
line, which seems to be a crowd
favorite. Uh,
>> did you know like when you write a line
like that, do you know like, okay,
that's going to be
>> I didn't even think of it as a big deal.
I was just like Bob the Builder
representing represent someone who like
come knock down these buildings or a
gentrifier, something like that. Um,
that's why I mean like usually when a
rapper or artist thinks they got a bar
and they stab it on the head, they
probably dropped the beat or some [__]
like that. [laughter]
>> I just kept going cuz it wasn't even
about it was actually about the the next
line.
>> The next line matters more. You know
what I'm saying? What about the
children? When I check a news channel
now I'm talking about
>> Palestine and Gazin, all of these
things. When I check a news channel, I
get a similar feeling but still we're
going to make it to heaven. High water
hell. Gave me chills a little bit. Um, I
be but all of this stuff that's going on
around the world and the kids that are
dying,
>> the adults, I mean, we gonna die. But
when when it's the kids, that's when I'm
[__] up about it. So, when I said,
"What about the children
and it's, you know what I'm saying? We
talking about Bob Builders and what
about the children?" I think that's just
like super cool cuz kids watch Bob the
Builder and then
>> we talking about true pain and people
dying and lives being lost and
>> just a lot of different, you know. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, okay. So, I got to ask you about the
clips feature. It's a really cool like
generational baton pass that you set up
at the end of the verse.
>> It was after then [music] I took my
talent right up to Virginia. They said
she a lover. [__] was gut or [__]
[music] was gritty. I could tell you
what he was, but let tell you what I'm
missing. Pay attention. What's missing
in my hood?
[music]
>> Did you write your way into the wanting
clips to be on the song or did you know
they were going to be on the song and
you wrote to pass off like that? Does
that make sense?
>> I get what you're saying. I I wrote it
to pass off and to push a verse like
that.
>> Okay. cuz the connection between us. I
mean,
>> but you knew they were going to be on
the song.
>> Yeah, for sure. I had pushed this at
first,
>> but I pushed everything back cuz I was
like, "Yo, I need Malice. There's no way
I can." You know what I'm saying? Even
>> because he stepped back into the back
into the light
>> or step back into rapping again. It's
like not I would love to do this because
I went to school in Virginia. [snorts]
Like I said on the record and being up
there, I heard everything about them. I
know I feel like I've met some of their
childhood friends. I I met people that
went to school with them like, "Oh, I
used to go to school at night." You know
what I'm saying? So, it was always a uh
a through line of like a connection and
it it was just perfect. You know what
I'm saying? It lined up perfect.
>> So, when you get that malice verse back,
that malice verse I think is a perfect
16. It's it's a perfect verse. Like,
what's the reaction when he delivers you
something that good?
>> Where [music] your bark at?
>> My ghetto's not your culture. [__]
really die here. So hard to say goodbye
is the only lullabi here. Kilos turning
[music] boys to men. Got to pick a side
here. Some would Jesus shuttles worth.
Some of us were not.
>> I loved it. It's very simple when you
hear stuff like
>> I I I seen him speaking about me in an
interview saying like um
they said I feel like I'm one of the
rappers that came from an era where you
had to rap.
>> I said my verse first. So I I didn't
know what was coming. And I just know
I'm going to put my best foot forward. I
didn't know Bob the Builder like I, you
know what I'm saying? I thought it was
pretty funny.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
>> But hearing somebody that you look up
to,
>> respect, you know what I'm saying? Both
of them
>> do their thing and then they men of
standards. You know what I'm saying?
[snorts] I I love [__] like that. You
know what I'm saying? That's what I do
this [__] for
>> is to be able to have these
conversations for you to say this one of
the best hip-hop songs you heard. I
don't know if you said this year or in
ever.
>> Ever. That's what
>> that's a beautiful thing right there.
You know what I'm saying? Because I do
it because I like it. I don't do it
because like, oh, all the homies in the
studio like this [__] It's like, no,
>> I really think this is a good
>> composition.
But when that exudes through the record
and and you give me that reaction or you
say that's how it makes you feel, it's
just like, okay, the message is being
toward told told, the stories is being
told and it's done in a real a real um
authentic type way that's authentic to
me.
>> Yeah.
>> You know what I'm saying? And how I
feel, how I grew up and stuff like that.
cuz like my stories are important.
>> Mhm.
>> For [clears throat] I know not just for
me but for my my little brothers, my
little my little cousins and other
little black kids that grew up how I
grew up. You know what I'm saying?
>> Yeah.
>> And it's kind of like inspiring to show
like, okay, it's a ABC. You can go to a
you can go to a from A to B. You can do
your thing. You know what I'm saying?
You can make a play.
>> You can you can grow. You ain't got to
be an artist. You can do anything you
want. But just
I don't know. I I keep a
a rearview mirror just to look back cuz
that's kind of what my music is about.
Like
uh being from the south,
I [laughter] I rap like I'm trying to
get a slave free. For sure.
>> For sure. And we [__] we [__] with bro.
But that's literally how I rap.
>> Right. Right.
>> You know what I'm saying? That's what I
care about. That's what my father cared
about.
>> Yeah.
>> Um I just got to acknowledge Malice's
final two bars tying perfectly into this
album. Candy Lady right there. Zombie
Land right there. So, if we're talking
about this album of ugly, dark light,
ugly beautiful, him painting that
picture of these apartments, giving you
the candy lady, the warmth, the zombie
land, everything that implies.
>> And then, I mean, he knew his assignment
cuz he says them apartments be the
perfect backdrop for any nightmare.
Tying it all the way full circle. And
then, yeah, you cut the beat out
assuming just cuz it's just like mic
drop.
>> I actually wrapped after that. Oh, you
did
>> after you heard his verse.
>> I already had it. I already had a second
part because the beat switch when you
hear those keys come in the beat switch
and I was like, "Okay, if we don't get
this in time,
>> it'll just be me and I'll do two
verses."
>> Oh, got it.
>> But it would be me and Pusher and I'll
do two verses. One at the end. I mean,
one at the beginning, one at the end,
half him in the middle. But it worked
out perfect. So those bars like
>> they were [__] great, but you
probably never want to hear.
>> Okay. All right. Um Okay. Okay. So, I
want to skip, as much as it pains me to
skip over Okay. Actually, no. I got to
ask you about a specific moment on G's.
>> Mhm.
>> One of the more unique perspectives or
stories I've heard in a rap verse before
where you tell this story about your car
getting broken into. I'm assuming it's a
real story.
>> Yep.
And then you explaining yourself like
checking yourself in real time and
contextualizing
feeling yourself getting angry and then
contextualizing this specific incident
within something larger. And then even
earlier in the verse you're talking
about when you have your own past of
doing similar things
by the door and I'm like what the [__]
is this? I knew what it was a stadium
right in the hood. My window was busted.
Now I feel the blood is rushing. [music]
Take a second and minute adjustment. Had
a couple things but it ain't find my
bang. [__] ain't really get nothing,
man. God dang. [__] took everything
[music] from the spare tires to the
spare chains and insurance papers and
some blunt break. What the [__] would
they want with that anyway? But we in
Atlanta, you can see the channels,
[music] man. That [__] going to happen
any day.
>> So, I'm assuming that's a a true story.
And I just maybe talk about that mind
switch cuz I feel like it's something
like really unique in in song, but also
like important for people to like think
about.
>> Super important.
>> And this going to be it's going to sound
kind of crazy to me. It's going to sound
very not to me to you.
I I said this to the homie the other
day. I was like, "Yo, I have so much
like empathy for my brothers, like black
people that it's like if I got
killed by robbed and killed by a black
man."
I told my homie, I was like, "You know
what? The first question I asked, like,
what did he go through all his life?
[laughter]
What the [__] did he deal with?" You
know what I'm saying? Like why do you
look at yourself being me? If you a
black man, you look at another black
man. It's representative of yourself in
a in a way. It's like how did you get
here to this self-hatred place? Now, I
probably won't like I'm not saying this
is actually like how I would do, but we
were having a conversation. I just
remember having that empathetic thought
in my head like, "How the [__] did he
get here? It ain't having nothing to do
with me.
>> I'm this is just whatever. I'm I got
robbed." Blah blah blah. But in real
life, like that empathy that I spoke in
that moment kind of made sent me for a
loop. I was like, "Yo, why do you think
like this?" And it and it goes back to
like my family, my father, and he's
being in the military. Him telling me
about his friends that that passed and
he went to the military when he was like
14. So, he just remembers carrying like
dead bodies like from being in this war,
doing dealing with all the [__] he had
to deal with.
>> Um,
>> I just I don't know. I see myself as a
empathetic person towards my people, but
in at the end of the song I say I ain't
tripping cuz I know who responsible.
It's the [__] that be claiming
we too thugged out which is blaming the
system. I'm just being one of those type
of guys like ah get your foot off my
[__] Like but let me do that. You know
what I'm saying? Because it's just the
>> No, it's valid. I think it's valid.
>> I think it's valid. And I think that's
one of the more important stories on
there that you could miss.
>> You could you could miss that whole
story and just think J is just rapping
again.
>> [laughter]
>> It's never that. It's literally
second verse. I'm telling you a whole
story. Get to the I'm telling you. I'm
telling you my real I'm saying Saints
and Falcons robbery weekend. [laughter]
I'm such a football here. I'm giving you
specific times,
>> dates, how it happened. Glass by the
door and I'm thinking about how dang I
used to try to like crack cards. Oh, I
broke in a car before, too. You know
what I'm saying? Why did you do that?
Why did you and your homies have that
over you? And it's just kind of like
adolescence, youth, the situations
people placed in.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh disenfranchised, you know what I'm
saying?
>> Lower circumstances, classes, all of
that. So, it's like
>> even saying I think it's funny. My mom
hate this line. I be thinking Martin was
wrong, Malcolm was right.
>> You know what I'm saying? It's very
simple, but at the same time, their
ideologies were
>> vastly different.
um in in their approach and stuff like
that. So just the contrast of all the
like how you would assume a person is
and then just getting into their
background and how they grew up and all
that stuff.
>> Like again, I wasn't trying to be too
metaphorical on here. I just wanted to
tell you a story of like why I'm
empathetic towards people that look like
me is because I've done the same things
and I see what we're up against or were
up against and still to this day.
>> Yeah.
>> And I just try to like shine light on
the mindset of a young black man from
East Atlanta that's grown, you know what
I'm saying? To a man
>> having fun with it. Bunch of young
[__] trying to feel numb to the pain.
I ain't tripping cuz I know who
responsible. The [music] [__]
they be claiming that we too thugged out
gangster. Ganga everybody bugged out.
>> Yeah, it's a really powerful story
especially when you understand the
context of it. I feel like hip-hop is
more and more giving you the empathetic
perspective, you know. I think
Kendrick's doing great work there and
just like really contextualizing it,
especially obviously for people like me
that just it's foreign to us, you know,
we grew up like that.
>> Um, okay. I wanted to jump into what I
perceive as act two of the album, which
is like this stretch of more melodic
songs.
>> Um, interesting approach in terms of
like grouping them all together. I think
the more traditional approach would be
kind of sparsing out those songs. So,
I'm wondering what the
>> thinking was kind of making this larger
act of these similar types of songs was.
just being a '9s baby and loving like
R&B and soulful sounds and
I just want like I I I went to like
vocal classes for this [__] Like I want
you to really understand like I'm I'm
really trying to sing. I'm really
singing here. I'm really like
>> Grammy nominated singer now.
>> Come on. We attacking these notes. Like
shout out Miss Beverly Johnson. Thank
you. Appreciate you. Love you.
[music]
Don't change.
>> She thinks the performance on wholehe
heartly is okay. I think it's really
good. But my she was like, "You did
okay."
She older lady. She like 80 something,
dog. Like [laughter] she don't care. She
just going to give it to me how it is
cuz she probably heard
>> [__] Ella Fitzgerald sing back in the
day or [laughter] something like
>> Right.
>> So with that being said, uh the it had
to be like that. It just had to be. Even
if it even if you feel like you lost
your vibe and you want more rap, I'm
going to rap forever, bro. But you going
to get these melodic songs, right? You
gonna get these songs with me and Jesse
Reyes, me and Maria, me and Don Toiver,
whole Harley, me, Todd Alan and Black.
Like, you're going to live in that. And
if it's just not for you, then I might
not even be the artist for you. Like,
>> but my fans appreciated that and I
appreciated it. And it and that's more
important cuz I do stuff when I like it.
It's not about like
it can't be based off anybody else's
visual. You know what I'm saying? It
can't be from their viewpoint or it's
just not authentic to me. So, I did that
intentionally. I wanted those to be in
that pocket. I wanted the mood to
switch.
>> I wanted to flip the mood on his head
all cuz I could have did a whole album
just full of like
>> communities, right?
>> You know what I'm saying? And I could
have did more G's and stuff like that,
but it was it didn't feel the time or
the place for it. It felt like me doing
this selfish moment of like, okay, I
really love these. I love this. Who the
[__] is this moment on what we own? You
know what I'm saying? I love that cuz
[__] Don T is like our Sam Sam Cook.
He's like Sam Cook to me.
>> I said that to him before. And
>> I love the confusion. And I love how
dark it is. It's vibey. Just listen to
it at 3:00 in the morning. Tell me
that's not like one of the greatest
songs you ever heard. You know what I'm
saying? 3:00 in the morning coming from
a long day or legally the club, any
situation like that is one of like my
favorite moments on the album along with
the melodic section in itself. [music] I
just wanna make it right.
Knee deep down in that pain. Call a
holiday to the sipping [music] a whole
that drink. Smoking a whole
>> I
>> feel like Cody Blue is like one of the
biggest bigger songs off of Forever
Story. Does that which is all melody? Is
that seeing the success and the kind of
fans taking a liking to that song gave
you more confidence to do like this
stretch or you're going to do it
anyways?
>> I'm going to do it anyway. I'm going to
do it anyway.
I would say that whole wholeheartly was
the oldest song on this project. It was
made in 2018.
>> Interesting. Okay.
>> 2018. Um
>> should say for the listeners that it was
the one that was nominated for best uh
melodic rap song at the Grammys. So
>> Oh yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. No,
definitely best melodic. And it's crazy
cuz it's the oldest one on the project
and
>> one of the first songs that brought me
into like, oh snap, I'm working with Tai
dollar signs. I'm in the industry, man.
It was one of those moments. So for that
to carry over to getting a Grammy with
me and my brother Black like me and
Black been doing this. We used to sleep
on each other couches and like we damn
near came up together. Um that and then
Todd Al sign one of the first artists
that I always like bought their album.
You know what I'm saying? The uh FreeT
album was my [__]
>> Um it's like full circle. Yeah, it's
really
>> it's all it's all super full circle and
it's my career has been like that the
whole time from the people that I love
to people I've been able to work with
and I don't know you just can't you
can't beat it. [snorts]
>> Okay, so let's uh so we get the vibe and
interlude which kind of gets us back
into transitions into the third act of
the album which is uh well at least is
my framing. I don't know if you thought
about the the album Axe, but
>> yeah,
>> definitely a switch on on Macaffy. Um
>> Macy McAfee
>> McAfee, sorry. Um there's enough raps in
this one song for an entire album
[laughter]
is so great. The the number of flows and
the switches, it's like
>> when you wrapped this live, I saw you
last week uh rap this live. I was like,
Jesus Christ,
>> it's a lot of information. It works
though. It works cuz the crowd is right
there with me. I give them little
moments to say that [__] like
>> Yeah. Well, there's a stretch of songs
where you wrapped this. I can't remember
exactly the set list or bunch of songs
like this back toback. I was like, how
the he must be doing cardio like
[laughter] or something. Jesus Christ.
>> For sure.
>> Um,
>> but there a lot of like I feel like
we're getting a lot of stories on the
last half of the album.
>> Yeah.
>> Little dog with a bite in the nice
[music] abusing turn looking for food
and look at the booty. Nice off. Maybe
the bougie [__] look good with the
lights off. He bust real dope moves. One
[music] dope, two loose screw. Three bad
black little [__] said [__] [__]
them. [__] you. [__] dudes up. Tough
dudes get touched to ash [music] to ash
and dust to dust. You best to bust the
rusty trusty dusty
>> on Macaffy being I'm not I'm not sure
exactly who they're about, but it feels
like you're talking to
maybe a younger generation cuz you open
with a little dog with a bite and a
bark, a nice heart.
>> I'm talking about the person on his own.
>> Oh, baby Kia. Oh, really? [laughter]
Okay. I was going to I was wondering if
he was symbolic, but it's literally him.
It's not lit him, but it's very symbolic
of like
>> what you might come across in Atlanta,
>> right?
>> And he was like the perfect person to
like help me set that up
>> cuz he like just represents a lot.
>> And he represents talent and and
intellectual um capacity being from
where he from.
>> He's like 18, 19 or something.
>> 18, 19, something like that. And I don't
know, I just appreciate this song for
what it is and how heavy it is. And then
the the story like you can hear a
subject matter what's going on in there.
It's not just like randomly thrown
together. It's literally like
>> stories that I've compiled through my
life
>> and people that I've seen that live that
>> those exact words.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Um who's on the outro?
There's a guy kind of giving you props
and
>> you're
>> Oh. Oh, you talking about at the end?
>> At the end very end of the song. Oh,
that's like
>> because you talk about someone right
before that. Uh, a blood hound. I think
he's a blood now. Uh, I don't even try
to show him a different route.
>> You've been thugging it since you know.
>> Is that Is that the guy you're talking
about? That
>> That's not him at the end. That's not
him at the end. But that's that's my
homie Dion, bro. I remember like I'm
talking about parkball and stuff like
that. And I just remember
he's the worst little human, bro. We was
like seven, eight years old. I'm like,
"Bro, why are you doing these things?
Why are you cussing so much? why
[laughter] you talking to this grown man
like that? And we just playing parkball.
And I was like, "Oh, this is what you
mean by bad apple mom. [laughter]
This is who you don't want me to hang
out." And I I kind of got that early. So
that song I hate that I said your name,
bro. [laughter] I hate it. I said I
bleep it out. No,
>> whatever.
>> But yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's just real
occurrences and just life that I seen in
Atlanta. Like just trying to paint ugly,
beautiful scenes and just get the
energy. You know what I'm saying? Feel
that.
>> I think [__] blood now. He bang guns
and take crumps. [music] He bugged out.
I don't even try and show him another
route. He been thuging it since a
younger. You know that we seen it coming
since days. I wobble shot.
>> You do feel like you get a portrait of
one aspect of Atlanta throughout this
project, you know, painting these
stories and
>> and not the happiest side of it. It's
not like the funnest. It's not the club
going scene.
>> It's kind of like the dark underworld
that you probably wouldn't even like
want to get into,
>> right? Okay. of blue
and kword I feel like is where we start
to get some of the resolution and
there's like little more hopeful themes
uh interspersed with
>> the ugliness. Um the Maria intro might
be my favorite part of the entire album.
It's so beautiful. Believe in males.
There's a reason for [music]
how the scene [singing] unfolds. Don't
stop.
>> Yeah, it's insane.
>> It's so good. Well, do you So, when
you're working with collaborators like
that, how much direction are you giving
her specifically? Like, do you tell them
like here's the theme of the song or is
>> 100%. That's what I did for this one
specifically. Usually I wouldn't have to
uh do that, but I just needed a certain
tone that she brought and I wanted it to
be um simple but like heavy and she
played it and sang it.
>> She played the piano.
>> No, she played the uh
>> the guitar.
>> She played the guitar on it and then I I
helped her with like some backgrounds. I
just sang a little bit in the
background. I was like, I just wanted
this to be your moment because I'm about
to just rap my life away and get to the
It's more of a re revol resolution type
song. Definitely. Definitely.
>> Yeah. It's kind of I mean, of Blue
itself is kind of its own little epic.
It's like a subtle epic because there's
like three or four parts to the song.
>> It's like a short film within. It's
really cool. Um,
and you so something I haven't talked
about that seems to come up throughout
the album, but really does come up on a
blue is this idea of cycles and being
stuck in cycles like um in the or in
your intro you say, "Are you following
the flames like a ch tail chasing a
dog?"
>> Yeah. Um later on in the verse you talk
about I'm going to ask you about who
this is about but essentially you have
that line about writing a light writing
a line sniff a white line pure writing a
line sniff a light line pure like this
cycle
>> I keep that personal
>> okay yeah
>> what I was talking about there
>> um but thematically the song seems to be
framed by Pastor Troy's vice versa
because you quote there's a refrain in
the song what if heaven was hell and
vice versa averse of vices is
>> I'm I'm assuming that's a call back to
Pastor Troy song
>> 100% [music]
>> told you go to hell would you tell I
cursed you
>> heaven [music] was hell and vice versa a
verse of vices writing and curs of the
grind of author defining purpose talking
to itself walking in circles in a seced
cabin [music] somewhere cold no phone
service so
>> and this whole song is a call back cuz
the first words you hear during the hook
is we got to find a place you know what
I'm saying and then I start going on
with that. But at the end of the song,
literally the last words I say, I think
I found it.
>> You know what I'm saying? I think I
found a place. And that place is love
essentially.
>> Um I [__] it. I go where the love is. I
think that's the place
>> that all like that is the opening to the
ending. You know what I'm saying? It's
all full circle. But also having him on
like the next song too was like super
player cuz I did the same thing on
Forever Story
>> with Yasine.
>> We had surround sound sample Miss Fat
Booty and then we actually had them on
Stars and
>> I try to like show love to my OGs and
everybody that's like inspired me and
I've been able to contact and get their
same
>> reciprocated love which is super great
for me. Um you're just super great just
being in a position where people that
you were inspired by kind of have the
same thing with you.
>> Um
but with that Yeah. Yeah. The Pastor
Troy moment was another part that was
just like full reflective of like kind
of how I grew up. And that song
specifically is just like
chiseling away like chipping away at the
ice trying to figure out like what is
this [__] all about? like
>> we got to find a place and just not
walking running in circles. You know
what I'm saying?
>> Just interested in what your perception
or interpretation of that concept of
what if heaven was hell and vice versa
because you end up in my interpretation
you end up rejecting it later in the
song
>> because you say [__] if heaven was hell
never rebel from the side of God. Um, so
I guess what was your interpretation of
Pastor Troy's Vice versa thematically
and why did you want to use it as kind
of the thematic framework of this song
>> on the opposite, right?
>> Yeah,
>> cuz just uh I love that song vice versa.
>> One of the most darkest dark ass song
for real. Even
>> to the point where he
>> reversed and cut out some of like the
verse on that part [laughter]
and I know what he said or that
>> Mother Mary stuff.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Crazy. [laughter]
concentr
>> but I'll just try to go go from the
other side like what you know what I'm
saying I said the same things but I'm
speaking more towards like no it's only
heaven like you know what I'm saying if
that's what you looking for if you
looking for love and stuff it's only
heaven like I wasn't really leaning to
like the the hell side of it because we
already got this God does like ugly I'm
talking about all of that type of stuff
so with this song it's more like it's
more of a resolve in it and
it's uh speaking on respect to like
honoring God.
>> Mhm.
>> Same. [music]
Repent and repeat and repent and repeat.
Descend and repent. I got to see it
through until it's finished. We all got
a sentence. We up again. Blank period
with a parenthesis. I've been searching
for [music] something with substance.
I'm clearly coming up with nothing. [__]
it. I go where the love is. I think
that's the
>> Yeah. So, it's interesting cuz Yeah. you
already talked about it, but um the song
eventually it's really cool how you set
up with the um the sinner repent and
repeat the center of repent and repeat I
got to finish it through until it's
finished. We all got a sentence sentence
we up against blank period that whole
work play is really cool but then yeah
you land on I'll go where the love is. I
think that's the place I might have
found it which feels like for me at
least that would have been a natural
transition into for keeps.
>> Mhm. But we get kword which is
definitely more gets back to the darker.
It's almost like the seduction of kword
being karma. Yeah. And you're kind of
personifying karma and talking about a
relationship with karma.
>> So I'm I'm curious for me kword is
you've been talking about cycles. Karma
to me is like the ultimate cycle. Not
only in this lifetime, but if you, you
know, research your karma in terms of
reincarnation, it's like
>> you'll actually be reborn until you get
a life cycle, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, I'm curious one, like why did you
want to kind of land the album with
Kword conceptually and like what like
what was the idea of personifying karma
and how it fits into the larger theme of
the album?
>> She come around, everybody calling her
[__] she don't give a [__] She like
that [__] when she pull [music] up
everybody dip goodbye like a long night
kiss.
>> Karma in itself is uh
as soon as you hear the word you get
like a bad connotation. You think like
karma ho but
>> I think the way I approached it was like
good karma. You know what I'm saying?
That's why I'm saying who can I call is
who can I call and all this stuff. Karma
got you good. Karma got you beat. Karma
got you good is kind of like where I was
standing with it. And the opposite side
is like karma got you beat. I don't care
if care I don't care if it come for me
because it's like I ain't doing nobody
wrong. Like you know what I'm saying? I
I would assume I would say I've been a
good man all my life. You know what I'm
saying? And of course I'm not perfect,
right?
>> Whatever. Whatever. But
>> my karma has like not proved to be or
maybe not to this point, but it hasn't
proved to be like evil dwelling. And it
could be like I don't know if it's on
the way. It could be sins of the
fathers. That's you know how that stuff
comes. But specifically when I was
speaking to Carmen on this one, it was
personifying it again, doubling down on
I don't [__] with the demon [__] All,
you know what I'm saying? Say on demon's
time, I think you sound foolish. Like
all of that dark [__] I was kind of
like throwing that under the bus and
just trying to like
show a brighter side to it. Cuz even at
the end of the verse, I say
>> and if I end his cycle here tonight
because I saw the light. You know what
I'm saying? That's the brightness to it.
And then you got Jesse coming in and
whatever the [__] she said. [laughter] I
always ask her like what was she saying?
It was it was it was simple though. It
was just saying uh
>> yeah she I have the translation. Okay.
So she said be careful with revenge. You
don't have to go and collect from
everyone and their mother. God takes
care of it. Have faith that God takes
care of it.
>> Yeah.
>> Which to me like for me for keeps feels
like more like an epilogue.
>> Like the conclusion of the album feels
like what you say if I do it right I can
end the cycle here tonight because I saw
the light. And then Jesse Reyes, who I'm
assuming is personifying karma.
>> Yeah,
>> 100%.
>> Giving that outro feels like a really
natural conclusion to ties up the ugly
beautiful motif, the dark lights.
If I do it right, then I can end the
cycle here tonight because I saw the
light. [music]
What is the resounding message that you
would want people to to take away from
the album in terms of um Yeah, I guess
just a message is is it karma? Is it
like good deeds will inspire good life
or like what do you
>> I feel like that's that's a good point
you can make from the album. Um,
and just perceiving yourself as like
not even perceiving yourself, just being
who you are naturally. You know what I'm
saying? If you're innately like a bad
person, then I'm sorry. Like be that, I
guess. You know what I'm saying? You
probably couldn't change that. That
comes to like my empathetic side to like
if somebody did something wrong to me,
like giving them that past. So this is
the conclusion would
essentially be just like living your
life with your best intentions, putting
your best foot forward.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> Um and just see the world how you see
it. Don't try to be like anybody else.
The her mentality like stuff like that
is not important to me. So I try to like
cut that off. You know what I'm saying?
Gang green it.
>> Yeah.
>> Um Okay. Well, we kind of got through
the entire album. I know we're coming up
on time, I guess. Um curious. Do you
know are you been working on the new any
new projects or you got anything in
mind? You
>> I got going on. Um as far as new music,
I mean,
>> it's probably going to be my best body
of work. M
>> I'm I'm 100% sure it's going to be like
my best body of work
just because of things I've learned and
me growing up into this music like I
didn't always think I was going to be an
artist. So me being in this industry
full man and I'm trying to and I'm
trying to understand the maneuvers and
then I understand it kind of got it. I
think it's going to be like a good a
good on to the next whatever chapter
this is. I'm kind of not rushing it. You
know what I'm saying? I'm enjoying this
Grammy [__] I'm enjoying listen I
listen to the project like a couple
nights. I was like, "This is a really
good [__] project." Like,
>> and it kind of grew with me. You know
what I'm saying? It's still growing. I
feel like even today, I'm still I'm not
hearing [__] that I wrote. I know that I
wrote the [__] It's not like, "Oh,
you're that smart. You just wrote some
[__] that you did." Nah, [snorts]
>> I'm just living with it and and watching
my words um
>> just manifest my life kind of. You know
what I'm saying? like the good karma
thing at that song karma always hey be
like not force myself to be a good
person but just like lead with love
essentially
>> right
>> um even songs like skate and stuff like
that like that just brings a part of my
childhood Atlanta like it's a super
Atlanta project
>> um
no I'm I'm in love with this album right
now though and I'm still thinking
forward like I'm I have stuff that I got
plans for with music and just different
things I want to try But I'm in that
place of like
unlearning, re relearning,
>> right?
>> So I can have another writing style for
the next project.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> And no, working through it, bro.
>> Yeah.
>> We on the road, so you know.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Know you got a busy
schedule. Yeah. Well, thank you for this
body of work. I mean, we're all still
sitting with it. There's a lot to learn
from it.
>> I mean, even prep prepping for this
episode, it goes way deeper than I
initially thought. So, it's just one of
those albums that I think grows on you,
grows with you. There's, you know,
there's more than enough kind of I
always say there's like portals can
learn, you know, we didn't talk about
the song with Vince, but even like that
even that that intro, you know, there's
a whole history lesson.
>> Oh, brother.
>> That VCRs, brother, that's one of my
favorite records as well.
>> Yeah.
>> Um,
>> yeah, it's a heavy,
>> but yeah, but there's there's little
stuff like references like that that
I've been really enjoying just like
digging into. So, we appreciate the the
work and I appreciate your time, man.
>> Anytime, bro.
>> Thank you, brother. [music]
>> [music]